<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Coppie of an act to be presented to his Grace, his Majesties High commissioner, and to the Right Honourable Estates of Parliament, anent gun-pouder and allom.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B43925</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">767618639</idno>
  <idno type="VID">212659</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240870199</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 767618639</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 767618639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1197A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R176597</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B43925)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 212659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 3025:10a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Coppie of an act to be presented to his Grace, his Majesties High commissioner, and to the Right Honourable Estates of Parliament, anent gun-pouder and allom.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>between 1681 and 1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date range of publication from text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Library.</note>
                  <note>With: Reasons for passing the act in favours of the undertakers for the making of gun-pouder and allom. [S.l. : s.n., 16--?].</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Gunpowder industry --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Alum industry --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="genre_form">Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:212659:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:212659:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:212659:2"/>
            <head>Coppie of an Act to be presented to his Grace, his Majesties high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner, and to the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Estates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, anent <hi>Gun-Pouder</hi> and <hi>Allom.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OUR Soveraign Lord, Considering the great Encouragements, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and given for the Erecting of Manufactories, by several Acts of Parliaments, Specially by the Act 1661, Entituled, <hi>Act for Erecting of Manufactories,</hi> and the Act 1681, Entituled, <hi>Act for Encouraging of Trade, and Manufactories;</hi> And that in pursuance thereof, and upon the Experience of the Benefit and Advantage redounding thereby to this Kingdom, particular Acts of Parliament have been made and past in favours of Manufactories, alreadie set up. As also, That this Kingdom having at present no <hi>Pouder-Mill,</hi> or work for making of <hi>Gun-Pouder,</hi> nor having ever had a Work for making of <hi>Allom,</hi> both which may nevertheless be very Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious as well for Export, as for necessary inward Consumption. Several persons have ingadged in a Co-partnarie for setting up and carrying on the said Works, which may be so useful, as said is. Therefore, His Majestie, with Advice and Consent of the Estates of Parliament, Statutes and Declares in Favours of Sir <hi>Alexander Hope</hi> of <hi>Kerss,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Dickson</hi> of <hi>Sornbegg, George Clerk, Junior</hi> and <hi>James Balfour,</hi> Merchants in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and their Co-partners, either already assumed, or to be assumed, and their Successors, Undertakers, of the said Works, That the said two Works for making of <hi>Gun-Pouder,</hi> and for making of <hi>Allom,</hi> when set up and Erected, shall be <hi>Manufactories,</hi> And that the foresaid Partners and Societie engadged for carrying on the said Works, shall be a Free and Lawful Incorporation, with all Priviledges usual, and shall have Right to, and brook and enjoy all the Priviledges and Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities provided in Favours of <hi>Manufactories</hi> by the foresaid Acts of Parliament; And particularly, and for the more special Amplification hereof, the hail Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, Liberties, and Immunities, granted to the Cloath and Linnen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactories, which are here holden as exprest. And farder, Because the said <hi>Allom-Work</hi> was never before erected in this Kingdom, and that the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers must necessarly at first be at great pains and Expences. Therfore, His Majestie with Advice and Consent foresaid, Statutes and Ordains, That the foresaid Undertakers thereof, shall have the sole power and Priviledge of making of the same, for the space of twenty five years, from and after the date hereof, and that it shall not be Leisom during that space, for any other person or persons to make <hi>Allom</hi> within this Kingdom, providing alwayes that the said Undertakers do set up the said <hi>Allom</hi> work with due Diligence. As also, That these Presents shall be without prejudice to the Importation of <hi>Allom</hi> from Forraign parts by Merchants, as they have been in Use to do before the making hereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:212659:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:212659:3"/>
            <head>REASONS FOR Passing the Act in Favours of the UN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERTAKERS for the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Gun-pouder</hi> and <hi>Allom.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1mo.</hi> Because the need of both <hi>Gun-pouder</hi> and <hi>Allom</hi> for the use of the Kingdom, is evident.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2do.</hi> Because we have formerly had <hi>Gun-pouder</hi> Mills; But thorow the want of due incouragement, they have long since been neglected and gone to Ruine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3tio.</hi> Because the foresaid works when set up, will not only hinder the necessary im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of both <hi>Gun-pouder</hi> and <hi>Allom;</hi> But this Kingdom having within it self the most of the Matterials necessary, the works may be quickly improven to furnish a good export.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4to.</hi> The setting up of the said work at first, where such works are quite out of use, will evidently require great pains and charges.</item>
               <item>5<seg rend="sup">to</seg>. If set up they would entertain a great many Idle and Poor people both in Work and Bread.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6to.</hi> The <hi>Allom</hi> work being wholly new, and which will need great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, and if once set up, would imploy and maintain at least a hundered per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, deserves the incouragement of the sole power of making <hi>Allom</hi> for twenty five years after the Grant of the Act; Specially when the same is sought with the provision; that in the mean time this priviledge shall not hinder the usual import.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7mo.</hi> There is also a special reason for the <hi>Pouder-work;</hi> because it may not only fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish <hi>Pouder</hi> for the Kings Forces and Magazins; But if at any time thorow accidents which often happen the <hi>Pouder</hi> in the publick Magazins should be spoiled, or grow weak, the foresaid <hi>Pouder-work</hi> would recover it from time to time, to its full strength, and when Ships of force go abroad they may be furnished by our own Mills.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8vo.</hi> It is found by experience of all other Nations, that Manufactories do Enrich those Kingdoms, where they are unanimously carried on.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>